Guide to the Ernestine Wiedenbach Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ernestine Wiedenbach papers
1912-1988
MS 1647
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.75
The papers consist of personal and professional files which document Ernestine Wiedenbach's childhood, student days at Wellesley College, and career as a faculty member in the Yale University School of Nursing, where she directed the nurse-midwifery educational program. The papers include correspondence, dating from her retirement in 1966 and writings relating to her professional career. Also present are diaries spanning almost her entire life, excluding the years she spent on the Yale faculty.
Wiedenbach, Ernestine
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Barbara B. Starr, 1993; C. Robert Bruns, 1994; and transferred from the Yale School of Nursing, 1994.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Ernestine Wiedenbach was born on August 18, 1900, in Hamburg, Germany. Her family moved to New York in 1909. She received a B.A. from Wellesley College in 1922, an R.N. from Johns Hopkins Hospital School of Nursing in 1925, an M.A. from Teachers College, Columbia University in 1934, and a certificate in nurse-midwifery from the Maternity Center Association School for Nurse-Midwives in New York in 1946, where she also taught until 1951. Wiedenbach joined the Yale faculty in 1952 as an instructor in maternity nursing. She was named an assistant professor of obstetric nursing in 1954 and an associate professor in 1956, when the Yale School of Nursing established a master's degree program under which she directed the major in maternal and newborn health nursing. She is the author of books used widely in nursing education. Wiedenbach retired in 1966. She died on March 8, 1998.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of personal and professional files which document Ernestine Wiedenbach's childhood, student days at Wellesley College, and career as a faculty member in the Yale University School of Nursing, where she directed the nurse-midwifery educational program. The papers include correspondence, dating from her retirement in 1966 and writings relating to her professional career. Also present are diaries spanning almost her entire life, excluding the years she spent on the Yale faculty.
Midwives; Nursing -- Study and teaching; Obstetrics; Wiedenbach, Ernestine; Wellesley College -- Students; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. School of Nursing
- Inventory
  - Biographical materials, 1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    General note
    [includes letters on retirement]
    - 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
    - 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Diaries [with accompanying loose materials]
    - 1912-1915, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - 1916
      - Volume I (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
      - Volume II (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Loose materials [Vol. II] (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Volume III (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
      - Volume IV (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
      - Volume V (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
    - 1918-1922 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Loose materials [1918] (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Loose materials [1919-1922] (Box 3, Folder 26-28)
    - 1936-1938 (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
    - 1946, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
    - 1948 (Box 3, Folder 33-34)
    - 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 35-36)
    - 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 37-38)
    - 1976-1979 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Memorabilia/clippings, 1956-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Writings
    - 1954, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - 1975, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - undated (Box 4, Folder 47)